<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A good and godly prayer to be said at all tymes of euery Christen, both man and woman, with a prayer vpon the Pater noster or paraphrase vpon the same.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1563</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 10 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09928</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20189</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103167</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838924</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838924</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3315</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09928)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3315)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1214:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A good and godly prayer to be said at all tymes of euery Christen, both man and woman, with a prayer vpon the Pater noster or paraphrase vpon the same.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Iohn Alde, for Mychell Lobley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprynted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno. 1563.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A.</note>
                  <note>Some print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lord's prayer --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Prayers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3315:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3315:1"/>
            <p>A good and a Godly Prayer to be ſaid at all tymes, of euery Chriſten, both man and woman, with a prayer vpon the Pater noſter or Paraphraſe vpon the ſame.</p>
            <p>¶ Imprynted at London by John Alde, for Mychell Lodley.</p>
            <p>Anno. 1563.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:3315:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3315:2"/>
            <head>¶ The prayer Of our Lorde.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lorde God oure Father in heauen wee thy myſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble chyldren vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon earthe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeche thee mercifully to loke vppon vs, &amp; lende vs thy gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, that thy name may be ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyfyed amonge vs and in all the worlde, through the pure preachinge of thy wurde, and trew knowledge and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of the ſame, and tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe earneſt charitie in our dayelye conuerſation and ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge, ſeclude thou graciouſly from vs all falſe doctrine and
<pb facs="tcp:3315:3"/>euill lyuyng, wherby thy wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy name mighte be blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and ſlaundered. Oh let thy kyngedome come, and be great to all ſynfull and blinde people, and ſuche as be holden captiue of the deuell and hys kyngdome, bring thou Lorde vs to trewe repentaunce &amp; to the knowledge of the trewe ſay the, in Ieſus Chriſte thy ſonne. Strengthen vs Lorde with thy grace, to doo thy wil in all godlye wurkes, and to ſuffer the ſame in lyfe and in death, in well and in wo, that our wil may be alwayes bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, offered vp and mortified. Geue vs our dayly bread, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue vs from all couetouſnes and immoderate carefulnes of the belly, that of thee we may be aſſured to haue abundau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce
<pb facs="tcp:3315:3"/>of all good thinges neceſſarye for vs, forgeue vs our treſpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, that we maye haue a glad and a quiete conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in thee, in that we receiue forgiuenes of oure ſynnes, as we be wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linge to forgeue all them that treſpaſſe agaynſt vs. And lead vs not into temptacion. But ſtrengthen vs Lord with thy ſpirite, to ſubdue the fleſhe to diſpiſe the world with the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities thereof, &amp; to ouercome the deuel with all his crafty aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults, and finally delyuer vs from all euel, both bodely and ghoſtlye, temporall and eternall, for thyne is the kyngdom, the power and the glory for euer. So be it.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3315:4"/>
O Almightye and euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyng God, Father, ſone and holy Ghoſte. Thou that haſt made heauen, earth and all thinges in theym con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned, haue mercy vppon me poore wretched ſinner, daylye aſſaulted with all kynde of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie and wretchednes, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeche thee o Father, for the loue of thy ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne Ieſus Chriſt, conſider my imperfection and haue mercy vpon me, encreace thy grace in me, my ſauiour, my redemer, my iuſtifier, for I come vnto thee O Lorde, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordinge vnto thy wurde, for thou haſt ſayd, come vnto me all ye that labor, &amp; are lade<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; I will refreſhe you, O my moſte mercifull Lord &amp; ſauiour, eaſe me of my burde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſynne, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che I haue vnrighteouſly com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mitted
<pb facs="tcp:3315:4"/>in deede, wurde and thought, and refreſh my ſoule with thy mercye, O reconcyle me with Iſope and I ſhalbe clean, and open my lippes (O Lorde) that my mouthe maye ſhewe thy prayſe, conſider my imperfection and haue mercye vppon me, and helpe it with thy great mercies, remember thyne olde wonted mercyes, faythfull promyſſes made to oure forefathers, Abraham. Iſaac and Iacob, and al other thy ſainctes in oure ſauioure Ieſu Chriſte, who being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed with infirmities and weakenes of the fleſhe come vnto thee (O LORDE) the well of lyfe and euerlaſtynge fountayne of their helth and ſaluation, and thou mercifully ſuſteyned them kepeſt them &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:3315:5"/>defendeſt them in all their te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations and tribulations, yf their feete any tyme ſlipte or went out of the waye, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted ſynne againſt thee, yet thy mercye was alwaye redy, ſo that thou by thy holy ſpirite haddeſt procured them agayn by repentaunce, ſo that they turned again vnto the, which conuerſion or turning agayn thou mercyfullye accepteſt at their handes, for becauſe they were deſirous to lyue perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in thy ſight, thou preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uedeſt theym, ſo that they be found faythful before thee, O Lorde thou arte the ſame, and thy years e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dure for euer. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſech thee O father bear my in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>firmities and imperfeccion, &amp; helpe it likewiſe with thy mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cye, if at any tyme I happen
<pb facs="tcp:3315:5"/>to fall and commytie ſynne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee, yet as thou ſaideſt by thyne Apoſtle Paule, lette thy grace at all tymes be ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient for me, ſo that I may im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly turne agayne bety<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me to repentaunce vnto thee, which conuerſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and turninge agayn, accepte alwayes at my ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds for Ieſus Chriſtes ſake. So ſhal I be found perfect be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee, for although y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirit be wyllynge, yet is the fleſſhe vntowarde and weake. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doo I not lay myne own righteouſnes before thee, for I knowe and confeſſe me, that is to ſaye, in my fleſſhe me, that is to ſaye, in my fleſſhe is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but playn miſery, wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chednes and ſynne. Therfore doo I come vnto thee, &amp; beſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che thee for Chriſtes ſake to er tende thy mercyfull hand to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde
<pb facs="tcp:3315:6"/>me, do away myne of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, for I know (O Lorde) that all grace and goodnes commeth of thee, and therfore arte thou prayſed (O Lorde) &amp; feared in the congregation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong thy ſainets, for thou on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly arte he that geueth victory. O Lorde God of hoſtes, and that as thou ſaydeſt by thy Prophete Zacharie, neyther throughe an hoſte of men nor through ſtrength, but through thy ſpirite. Therfore I beſech thee geue me not only ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth &amp; knowledge of thee, but alſo a redy earneſt purpoſe &amp; wyll to ſubdue myne affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and graunte me grace at all tymes too lyue as thou in thy holye wurd haſt preſcribed vnto me moreouer I beſech thee make me perfecte in thy ſighte, that
<pb facs="tcp:3315:6"/>I may re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dre co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinual thankes by Ieſus Chriſte vnto thee, &amp; where as I haue not hetherto endeuoured my ſelf, according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> power whiche thou haſte gene<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me to lyue after thy wil, I praye thee of forgeuenes for Chriſtes ſake thine only ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne our Lord, and now I proteſte before thee through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> helpe of thy holy ſpirite, to order my li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe from henceforth accordinge to thy wurd, and to walk per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly before thee. Neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe I beſech thee for Chriſtes ſake at al times to bear the im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perfection that any tyme is founde in me and delyuer me by thy power and mercye, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creace my faythe O my rede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, encreace my fayth O my fauiour encreace my fayth O my iuſtifier, encreace faith ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pe,
<pb facs="tcp:3315:7"/>loue, charitie and all other vertues conſonaunte, &amp; agrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to a godly lyfe, for I come vnto thee (O Lorde) the Well and euerlaſtinge Fountayne of all helth &amp; ſaluacion. O my heauenly father, let me and al other which ſeek thy wurde to thentent to forſake ſinne &amp; to ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de their liues, liue in thy ſight, I thanke thee (O Lord) with all my harte, ſoule and mynde, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it hath pleaſed thee of thy great mercye and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to creat and fourme me of the molde of the earth, &amp; geue me members needefull to my body, and that it hath pleaſed thee to preſerue alwhich (thou haſt created in me) ſithe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s the tyme of thy creatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vntil now, &amp; that it hath pleaſed thee to deliuer me fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the hour of te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacion,
<pb facs="tcp:3315:7"/>and in my tribulacion, aſwel ſlepig as wakig whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I was forgetful of thee as whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I remembred to cal vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thee &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it hath pleaſed thee to mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter to my neceſſities, meat, drinke and clothynge and as inward reioyſing, quietnes of mynd, helth of bodie and ſuch lyke, and that it hathe pleaſed thee to geue me this woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be my wyfe as a remedie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latie and comforte in al my ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities. Graunt vs grace (O Lorde) truely together to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour loue and ſerue thee, for I know that whatſoeuer I do, either good or euil, it ſhalbe re warded of thee. Lighten vs therfore dayly, I beſeche thee with thy grace that we maye gouerne our ſelues, our houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde and chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which thou
<pb facs="tcp:3315:8"/>haſt geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs in the true faith, feare and knowledge of thee, ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> it maye bee an acceptable ſacrifice vnto thee, by Ieſus Chriſte our lord. And ſeyng it hath pleſed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> O father to ligh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inward eies of my mynd with thy grace, &amp; to cal me fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the great blyndenes of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce and ſynne, wherein al men are born, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> knowledge of thee, let it now muche more (as ſainct Paule ſayth) pleaſe thee to preſerue me &amp; all other whom thou haſt called, which be dayly oppreſſed by ſynne, &amp; deſire to turne and come vnto thee (of what tunge or nacion whatſoeuer thei be) thorough the whole worlde, and ſeing it hath pleaſed thee to cal me by grace to the knowledge of thy wurd, &amp; geue me a wil to ſeek
<pb facs="tcp:3315:8"/>it to loue &amp; beleue in it, let it be thy will to directe my wayes that I erre not, ſtaye my feete with thy holy ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, &amp; preſerue me with thyne arme, for I am els farre to weak, for without thee I can doo nothing. O let me lyue in thy ſight O Lord, and put me not oute from thy preſence, but geue me a newe hart and a newe ſpirite, that I maye alwayes cal vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thee in tyme of my trouble, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer thee an acceptable ſacry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyce by Ieſus Chriſte before thee, euen the fruyte of thoſe lyppes, which confeſſe thy na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, geue me grace (O lord) pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently to receyue the Cup of helth &amp; ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at thy ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, &amp; call vpon thy name in the tyme of mine aduerſitie, O hear my prayer I beſech thee lette my
<pb facs="tcp:3315:9"/>power and pleaſure be alway in the frute of the tree of lyfe, whiche is in the Paradyſe of God, O accept theſe volenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſacrifices at my handes as the ſweet ſmell of incence, and let the lifting vp of my ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des be an euenig ſacrifice, pleaſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and acceptable vnto thee tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough Ieſus Chriſte oure Lorde, to whome be euerlaſting prayſe honour and glo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rie, now &amp; euer. Amen.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:3315:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
